<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Data Wonder]]></title>
  <link href="http://datawonder.co/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://datawonder.co/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-30T17:14:16-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://datawonder.co/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Veronda]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Data Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://datawonder.co/blog/2013/01/30/first-data-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://datawonder.co/blog/2013/01/30/first-data-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wow, just finished an intensive month of interviewing with a lot of companies and finding an apartment. I can now relax a little bit before starting my new job and get back on my path to data learning.  Although I haven&#8217;t been doing too much with Kaggle, I have kept an eye out for what are some good resources and found a lot of different blogs and postings related to machine learning and data science to see what other people are doing in this field.  I enjoy reading news and have decided to make as much of that related to what I want to learn as possible.  I started a year ago or so with <a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/">Hacker News</a> and have found it to be a treasure trove of good advice for programming and occasionally data-related articles popup on the front-page as well, <a href="http://conductrics.com/data-science-resources-2">like today for example</a>.</p>

<p>I also attended a meeting of the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/NYC-Machine-Learning/events/97871782/">NYC Machine Learning Meetup group</a>, which was a talk given by a Spotify employee about collaborative filtering as applied to music recommendations.  Although a lot of the material was just simply beyond comprehension as I wasn&#8217;t too familiar with the techniques and equations used, I have learned that supervised collaborative filtering is pretty much matrix completion, which really drives home the point that I really need to refresh myself on Linear Algebra.  It was also very useful to see how other companies are applying recommendation techniques to their business.</p>

<p>Anyway, my increased reading of data-related articles has already paid off as it has led me to work on my first data &#8220;project&#8221;. In December, there were <a href="http://www.empiricalzeal.com/2012/12/24/are-mass-shootings-really-random-events-a-look-at-the-us-numbers/?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=are-mass-shootings-really-random-events-a-look-at-the-us-numbers">two</a> very <a href="http://www.empiricalzeal.com/2012/12/21/what-does-randomness-look-like/">interesting</a> blog posts about what does randomness truly look like and I actually learned something practical about Poisson distributions.  I first learned about Poisson Distributions in college as taught by my physics roommate, but all I understood was that it was a discrete distribution as opposed to the continuous nature of Gaussian distributions.  However, if you asked me where to apply Poisson distributions, I probably would be at a lost.  Now, I&#8217;ve learned one interesting application is it could help answer if an observed pattern of events are expected or if something else is happening.  For example, take the average number of people attacked by sharks every year.  According to Wikipedia, it&#8217;s around 100 worldwide with about 17 fatalities.  As most people intuitively know, just because the average is 100, that doesn&#8217;t mean that there will be exactly 100 shark attacks this year or next year, it just means that it is the average that it tends to be.  Now suppose we observe a few years in a row of higher shark-attack activity, say 150-200, the question one might ask is: &#8220;is this streak just a random coincidence or is there an actual change in the underlying pattern?&#8221;  Thanks to the above mentioned blog-posts, one can use a Poisson distribution to help answer that question.</p>

<p>Therefore, for my next blog post (still not sure on what publishing schedule to work with, but I recently read some good advice in that I should focus on quality not quantity with blog-posts), I will try to answer a question that popped into my mind recently.  Lately, there has been been a lot of a kerfuffle lately in NYC about subway deaths (sorry for the morbidity that follows).  There has been an unusually high amount of deaths in the subway and it&#8217;s received a lot of attention in the media and by the Mayor&#8217;s office.  Given the current rate, the media is saying there will be <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/nyc-on-pace-for-nearly-100-subways-deaths-in-2013-2013-1">100 subway deaths this year</a> (double that of last year), which my intuition thinks is just flat-out wrong and can be statistically disproven using a Poisson Distribution.  So, I&#8217;ll gather up historical data, try to apply a Poisson distribution and see if I can show that this is just a random streak instead of a more serious trend.  Perhaps a bit more ambitiously, I wonder if I could try to forecast how many subway deaths will actually occur this year.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World!]]></title>
    <link href="http://datawonder.co/blog/2012/12/17/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://datawonder.co/blog/2012/12/17/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello, World!  For a long time, I have had the feeling that <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/steveyegge2/you-should-write-blogs">I should write a blog</a>, as inspired by Steve Yegge and other great bloggers.  The final impetus was <a href="http://statspotting.com/2012/12/just-finish-everything/">this post</a> I saw on Hacker News that basically said, &#8220;you should finish everything.&#8221;  The post really spoke to me because I have had that same attitude of, &#8220;I could finish it if I wanted.&#8221;  Additionally, I always had to repeat the mantra, &#8220;always finish what you start&#8221; while practicing Tae-Kwon-Do way back in the day.</p>

<p>The timing of the post worked out too because I have always been interested in becoming some form of machine learning expert or data scientist (the naming doesn&#8217;t matter, just something related to intelligent applications of computing and dealing with data, I guess I will still work on what that means).  Last year I joined a company and, given a choice between two teams, I joined a team with the understanding I would get to write a machine learning componenet for the team&#8217;s product.  Now that hasn&#8217;t panned out and I just realized, why do I need to have a job related to what I want to do in order to gain experience?  I am in the fortunate and rare job-field where I can practice what I want to do on my own.  I have already taken a machine learning course while I was at the University of Rochester and attended as many machine learning talks as I could and was a member of the machine learning committee at my job.  I have also recently come across this really great website, <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/About">Kaggle</a>, which is basically a data competition site that should give me exactly the experience I have been looking for&#8211; working with real data sets in an environment where I can receive constructive feedback as to how I&#8217;m doing.</p>

<p>While I am still not sure how exactly this blog is going to play out, I am thinking that basically it will follow me on my 10,000 hour journey to becoming an expert on data.  Why 10,000 hours?  Peter Norvig, who has written probably the <a href="http://aima.cs.berkeley.edu/">most elucidating textbook</a> ever, wrote an excellent piece about <a href="http://www.norvig.com/21-days.html">learning to teach yourself to programming in 10 years</a>.  It provides further links to an interesting study that found the best performers to come out of Julliard School were the ones that practiced obessively and time and time again, it appears that those that have 10 years experience in something get really good at it.  I just realized that I am approaching the 10 year mark of writing software and since I have worked at a major software company, I feel comfortable saying that I am pretty good at software development.  Although I enjoy writing software, I find that what I enjoy most is uncovering morsels of data from everywhere.  Some of my favorite stories revolve around clever use of data, such as <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/kevin-drum/2010/09/counterintuitive-world">how to best armor planes</a> given the bullet holes in them (the answer is counter-intuitive).  An even more amazing story is how an 18&#8217;th century US Naval officer, <a href="http://trends.wordpress.com/2009/11/23/ships-and-tools/">using data from ships logs</a> that had been lying around unused and was about to be thrown out was able to save, &#8220;American Ships $2.5 million a year and the global fleets perhaps more than $10 million a year&#8221; (which translates to well over $200 million in today&#8217;s money!).  Regardless of whether or not Big Data is just a fad, it is clear that the ability to use data wisely will only become more important in this day and age.</p>

<p>How to measure success towards my goal?  For one, I think I will take a literal approach and record how many hours I spend working on data.  Other ideas are if other people, journalist or whoever comes to me with questions about their data or data science (I am using these terms loosely by the way).</p>

<p>Anyway, I feel my writing thus far really needs a lot of work and hopefully I&#8217;ll improve with practice.  I look forward to many hours of data fun!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
