<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: SideProject | Data Wonder]]></title>
  <link href="http://http://datawonder.co//blog/categories/sideproject/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://http://datawonder.co//"/>
  <updated>2014-01-16T01:08:08-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://http://datawonder.co//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Veronda]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Detour]]></title>
    <link href="http://http://datawonder.co//blog/2012/12/19/a-detour/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://http://datawonder.co//blog/2012/12/19/a-detour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I decided to take a small detour along my data-driven path because, as mentioned in my previous post, I don&rsquo;t quite have supreme expertise as a software developer.  So my more immediate short-term goal is to continue down that path, but my side-project is still related in a way.  I will be working on a quick Rails application.  Why Rails?  My experience and background mostly point to me being solely a Java programmer and although I have dabled in other languages throughout school and on my own, it&rsquo;s high time I &ldquo;gain my own experience&rdquo; rather than relying on a job to provide me with a well-rounded background.  So unfortunately, at this point I sound a lot like the type of person Steve Yegge <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/steveyegge2/five-essential-phone-screen-questions">declares as an anti-pattern for hiring</a> a candidate (tl;dr, see &ldquo;Bad-Sign #1 at the bottom, although I can handily answer those questions as posed) and I am going to change that with this application by learning a bit of Rails as I write this quick app.  Another reason is that I have always enjoyed the neat stuff that Ruby provides and I am using Heroku as my hosting solution, so the Rails integration is something to look forward to playing around with.</p>

<p>What is it that I will be writing?  It&rsquo;s an application to keep track of my 10,000 hour goal and how much time I have spent on it.  Shockingly on GitHub, there is no project called &ldquo;YakShaving&rdquo; and so that is what my project will be called.  For some readers, you may be wondering why &ldquo;YakShaving&rdquo; and why it is shocking there is no project called that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
